<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, vpon the wordes of Paul the Apostle vnto Timothie, Epist. 1. Chap. 4. vers. 8 Preached at Litlecot, in the Chappel of the right honourable, Sir John Pompham, knight, lord chiefe justice, of England, before his honourable Lordeshippe, and to the assemblie there, the 17. of Iulie, 1597. By Charles Pinner, minister of the Church of Wotton Basset, in North-Wiltshire.</title>
            <author>Pinner, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09675</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114276</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849502</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849502</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14652</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09675)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14652)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1527:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, vpon the wordes of Paul the Apostle vnto Timothie, Epist. 1. Chap. 4. vers. 8 Preached at Litlecot, in the Chappel of the right honourable, Sir John Pompham, knight, lord chiefe justice, of England, before his honourable Lordeshippe, and to the assemblie there, the 17. of Iulie, 1597. By Charles Pinner, minister of the Church of Wotton Basset, in North-Wiltshire.</title>
                  <author>Pinner, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes, and are to bee solde [by J. Broome in London] in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Book-seller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14652:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14652:1"/>
            <p>SERMON, VPON the wordes of Paul the Apoſtle vnto Timothie, Epiſt. 1. Chap. 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PREACHED AT LITLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cot,</hi> in the Chappel of the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, SIR IOHN POMPHAM, Knight, Lord chiefe Iuſtice, of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, before his honourable Lordeſhippe, and to the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie there, the 17. of <hi>Iulie,</hi> 1597.</p>
            <p>By CHARLES PINNER, Miniſter of <hi>the Church of Wotton Baſſet, in North-Wiltſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Tim. 6. verſe 6.</bibl>
               <p>But godlineſſe is greate gaine, with ſufficiencie.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at Oxford by Ioſeph Barnes, and are to bee ſolde in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Bible. 1597.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14652:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14652:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVL, Maſter IOHN SIMS, of Charde, in the Countie of Somerſet, <hi>grace, and peace from God in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, it may be marveiled of ſome, if not of your ſelfe, that I ſhould bee thus familiar, as you ſee, &amp; cannot but be ſeene of many. Whom I pray to take this for my excuſe, (which vnfainedly I ſpeake, and from my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hart.) That a deſire, conceiued now a good while ſince, engendered by a report of your godly friendes &amp; mine, is now come vnto the birth, by ſpeech with your ſelfe: and this it was; that I wiſhed once to know you, as novve in part I do, and ſhal, I truſt, more fully in time to come. For why ſhould you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue mee of the farther fruite of that, (and call it I muſt your godlineſſe by the very name:) which ſo taſted in part already, I could not but forth with tel and teſtifie vnto others alſo, that ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14652:3"/>great zeale of true Religion hath ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome bin planted in ſo tender yeares: and I looke to the time of the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. For the watering, and groweth whereof (as much as my poore penne &amp; penſil can performe herein) behold againe the gaine of godlines, preſented to your eie; and yet vnpreſented: for what pen, or penſill can deliuer her as ſhee is? whom (as Cicero ſaith of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, their vertue, a weake ſhadow ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) if with the eies of our body wee might beholde, it woulde make vs to loue her, not without wonder. But we muſt tarry the time, till we ſee her, and him togither, of whom S. Iohn ſaith, <hi>Dearely beloued, now are we the ſonnes of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>but yet it appeareth not what we ſhall be: howbeit we know that when he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, we ſhall bee like him: for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> And then, and there alſo ſhall we ſee this godlineſſe, which wee deſire: which, till that appearing, (and now in this age of ſo great vngodlines, whoſe ſpreade hath overſhadowed ſo much of this land) ſo little appeareth,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14652:3"/>that ſhee dareth not almoſt be known by this her name of godlines, for fear of the flouts, which without fear do flow ſo faſt from the vngodly; of which this is not the leaſt, when they ſay to anie perſon, whom they moſt deſpiſe, <hi>O you are very godly.</hi> Whoſe mouthes muſt be ſtopped, <hi>which speake prowde thinges,</hi> as Iude ſaith, <hi>hauing mens perſons in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude. 16.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe of aduantage.</hi> And to ſtoppe their mouthes; or if not that, to open the mouth of godlines to ſpeak for her ſelfe, I ſay not, how praiſe-worthy ſhe is, vnto whom al praiſe is due; but, how profitable vnto vs: I then preached, &amp; now haue publiſhed this litle Sermon. Accept it, as you finde it; and my ſelfe, by it. The Lord Ieſus preſerue you, &amp; encreaſe in you the graces of his holy ſpirite, <hi>Amen. From Wotton Baſſet the</hi> 23. <hi>of Iulie.</hi> 1597.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in Chriſt, <hi>CHARLES PINNER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:14652:4"/>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14652:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. Tim. Chap. 4. verſ. 8.</bibl>
                  <p>For bodilie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe profiteth litle: but Godlineſſe is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable vnto all thinges; as having the promiſe of the life preſent, and of that that is to come.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F the wound, &amp; cure of ſinne; or rather of the death of ſinne in the ſoale, &amp; the life of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe by Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Chaplaine that day preached of ſuch matter. Iohn. 5.15.</note> we haue heard alreadie. Of the which our Sauiour ſaith in the <hi>5.</hi> of Iohn, <hi>Verilie verilie I ſay vnto you, the houre ſhall come and now is, when the dead ſhal heare the voice of the ſon of God: and they that heare it ſhall liue.</hi> And wee haue heard, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, and liue in God. Of the courſe of which life in godlineſſe, and the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed benefite of the ſame, wee haue nowe to heare farther out of this ſentence of the Apoſtle: which depending on the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as a reaſon of his exhortation there
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14652:5"/>vnto Godlineſſe, containeth doctrine, &amp; admonition: Doctrine, for the whole Church; as admonition likewiſe for the ſame: but, properlie for Timothie; a man, and a miniſter, young in yeares, but graue and auſtere in manners, verie much, if not too much: hauing alwaies before his eies that dutie, which this our Apoſtle himſelfe otherwiſe embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.27.</note> where hee ſaith, <hi>I beate downe my body, and bring into ſubiection, leaſt by anye meanes vvhen I haue preached vnto others, I my ſelfe ſhould bee reiected.</hi> Yet miſſing the rule, of too much ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or too little deſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in going too far, (as <hi>Nimium,</hi> and <hi>Parum, <hi>Too much,</hi>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>too litle,</hi> are ſtill in our way for every godly duty:) the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth him back, as els where by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial admoniſhment to look vnto his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke; ſo here by theſe generall wordes, <hi>Bodily exerciſe profiteth litle:</hi> and leſſe in deede he meaneth, then Timothy took it. Wherein to bleare his eies a litle, who ſtared to much on it, he ſetteth before him another obiect, ſo much more greate &amp;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14652:5"/>excellent, that, becauſe it ſwalloweth vp the firſt, wee alſo will ſtay our ſelues in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this, in theſe words, <hi>but godlineſſe is profitable vnto all thinges, as having the promiſe of the life preſent, and of that that is to come.</hi> Wherein wee haue two pointes, a doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and the ſame aſſured by a reaſon to vs: the doctrine, in theſe wordes, <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is profitable vnto all thinges:</hi> the Reaſon, in theſe, as <hi>having the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the life preſent, and of that that is to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the which wee may note, firſt, how the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, which is, <hi>abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive,</hi> as they ſay, in the <hi>Abſtract,</hi> and not in the <hi>concrets;</hi> ſchoole-rearmes, but of eaſie vnderſtanding; the one, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the qualitie alone and by it ſelfe conſidered; the other, the ſubiect, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with the qualitie, or in whome is that qualitie. And this no doubt alſo but the Apoſtle meaneth, namelie, that the godlie perſon hath the promiſe; and yet hee both not ſo ſpeake, but ſaith, that Godlines hath the promiſe: and why?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14652:6"/>becauſe the godlie perſon, for his godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not elſe; but godlineſſe, for it ſelfe; it being ſuch a thing, and ſo like vnto God himſelfe, that hee cannot but bleſſe it, euen now in this life preſent, &amp; eſpeciallie in that that is to come; and thereof hath made and given his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to vs, that wee not onely ſhoulde haue it, and take it, when it commeth; but alſo ſhoulde hope and waite for it; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when we haue it not. From whence ariſeth the truth of this ſentence or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that <hi>Godlineſſe is profitable vnto all thinges,</hi> as that which giveth vs al thinges either in preſent poſſeſſion, or expectation.</p>
            <p>Many diſpute many thinges; &amp; many deſires, &amp; purpoſes haue wee: but in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing our mindes more corrupt &amp; deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the truth, then in this, if without, or beſide godlines, wee count any thing to be gaine or profite. Whoſe minds not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding are ſo corrupt, &amp; ſo deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the truth, that any thinge (almoſt) we account gaine &amp; profite without god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines: or at the leaſt all the godlines we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14652:6"/>haue or doe beſire, is gaine &amp; profite. For if other gaine we haue, we haue godlines enough, though we haue none in deede; &amp; yet haue as much, as wee deſire. Men of this making altogether this out Apoſtle painteth out in the <hi>6.</hi> Chap. of this Epiſt. the <hi>5.</hi> &amp; <hi>6.</hi> verſes; whome he ſaith to bee <hi>men of corrupt mindes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; deſtitute of the truth, which thinke gaine to be god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lines.</hi> What is that? in wit, this: their godlines, or al the godlines they care for, is gaine, according to their corrupte mindes, &amp; deſtitute of the truth; embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing any in the world, as good &amp; profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and letting godlines alone: of which the paſſe not a pin, and care nothing of it, as nothing worth, if ſo they may attaine their other deſires. And that this is the meaning, it is plaine, in that the Apoſtle contradicteth it in theſe wordes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but, ſaith he, <hi>Godlines is greate gaine.</hi> Not onely gaine, but great gaine, and if we will haue that expounded too, the Apoſtle ſaith in our Text, that <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is profitable vnto all thinges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherfore we neede goe no further for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14652:7"/>weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to ſlay the madnes of Atheiſme, that is, vngodlines it ſelfe, which ſetteth godlines at naught, and teacheth men to mocke at it, as a thing of nothing: and a thouſand things we deſire as good &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable; but godlines with thouſandes is good for nothing. And Religion, though it ſelfe honourable, yet if, as it hath the nature, ſo the name of goodlines (euen as this is her name alſo; for what is religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but godlines; and what is godlines, but religion?) yet, in this other name of hers wee cannot abide her; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the name of godlineſſe, is a deriſion. For I tell you, he hath a fine wit, and hitteth his neighbour home, as he thinketh, which can hang the lip, and ſay, O you are very godly, <hi>O tempora, ô mores, <hi>ô times ô manners,</hi>
               </hi> ſaith he, who ſaw the diſcipline of the city of Rome ſo weake, that one Catelin, a ſeditious rakehel, could ſit, and be ſeene in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate amongſt them. And we muſt ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our griefe and ſay nothing, to ſee the Church of God defiled with thouſandes of thoſe, &amp; ſitting almoſt in the Senate,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14652:7"/>and chiefeſt roomes amongſt vs, who not only ſecretly vndermine, but euen bid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen battaile (almoſt) vnto the name of godlines: theſe being, I feare, the times, of which Peter by a ſpecial reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance vnto the faithful, foretold, ſaying,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.3.4</note> 
               <hi>This firſt vnderſtand, that there ſhall come in the laſt daies mockers, walking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their owne luſts, and ſaying, when is the promiſe of his comming?</hi> ſuch, as even ſtowted the Lord, and grieued the godly, and gaue complainte before vnto the Prophet Malachie in the <hi>3.</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>Your wordes haue beene ſtoute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, ſaith the Lord: yet yee ſaie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.13.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>what haue we ſpoken againſt thee? ye haue ſaide, it is in vaine to ſerue God; and what profit is it that we haue kept his commandement, and that we wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked humbly before the Lord of hoſts. Yea now we counte the prowde bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: euen they that worke wickednes are ſet vp; and they that tempt God, yea they are deliuered.</hi> And they had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen wearied the Lord herewith, as the Prophete complaineth in the former
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14652:8"/>Chapter,<note place="margin">Mal. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>Yee haue wearied the Lorde with your wordes,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>yet yee ſaie, wherein haue we wearied him? in that yee ſay, euery one that doth euill, is good in the ſight of the Lord, and hee delighteth in them: or, where is the God of iudgement?</hi> and theſe haue euen wearied the Lord, and vs; as many, as at this time embrace godlines: and yet they ſaie, wherin haue we wearied you? in that ye ſay, and ſay lowdly, and lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with the greateſt ſkorne, we are foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and buſie fellowes.</p>
            <p>But the vomit of theſe men is loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and we will leaue it: and for the praiſe, and price of godlines, wil come to the proofe of that, which the Apoſtle hath ſaide of it, as we haue heard, namely, that <hi>Godlines is profitable vnto all things.</hi> And this proofe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in the words next following, implying a reaſon of the former ſpeech or ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in theſe words, as <hi>having the promiſe of the life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and of that that is to come.</hi> And this reaſon is ſtrong from a ſufficient di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of all thinges. For all thinges are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14652:8"/>contained in this life preſent, and in that that is to come. And therefore godlines muſt needs be profitable vnto al things, ſith nothing, neither here, nor heereafter can be wiſhed, which it bringes not with it. For though the Apoſtle only ſaieth, it hath the promiſe of this life, &amp; that life, he meaneth, as alſo he ſpeaketh in the <hi>17</hi> of the <hi>Actes, Life and breath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17.25.</note> 
               <hi>and all things;</hi> and as the Philoſopher ſpeaketh, all things <hi>ad benè beate<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vivendum, <hi>to liue well and bleſſedly.</hi>
               </hi> For life elſe were nothing, if wee ſhoulde want thoſe things that pertaine to bleſſednes. And though ſome maie thinke that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle commeth ſhort of the matter, &amp; ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not home enough, ſaying, that god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines hath the promiſe, &amp; not the thing; yet this is al one in deede, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering who is the promiſer, <hi>God that cannot lie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as other where he ſaith. And becauſe wee cannot haue al our happines at once, but ſome is here in this life preſent, and more hereafter in the life to come; for aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the whole we haue his promiſe, which is alwaies as good as performaunce it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14652:9"/>ſelfe. <hi>For whoſoeuer,</hi> ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Siracke, truſted in the Lord, and was confounded?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 2.11.</note> O then, who is wiſe, &amp; wil be rich, and honourable, and haue true ſtrength, and beauty, and health, &amp; peace, and bleſſednes with God? euen the man, that is godly; which walketh with God, yea and talketh with him: as it is ſaide of <hi>Henoch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 5.22. &amp; 6.9. &amp; 17.1.</note> 
               <hi>Noah, and Abraham,</hi> that they were <hi>iuſt and vpright men in their time, and walked with God.</hi> Euen as this is the ende of our deliuerance, <hi>that we,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.74.75.</note> as <hi>Zacherie</hi> ſaith, <hi>being deliuered out of the hands of our enemies, might ſerue him without feare, in holines, &amp; righteouſneſſe before him, or in his ſight, all the daies of our life:</hi> that wee ſhould walke, and talke with God; and hauing our delighte in the lawe of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.2.</note> ſhoulde meditate therein day and night; that we ſhould loue, feare, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him in all our waies, and ſo wante nothing, which we would &amp; ſhould haue, either in this life preſent, or in that that is to come.</p>
            <p>But here groweth a queſtion: what it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14652:9"/>meaneth then, that euen vngodlineſſe it ſelfe hath, or ſeemeth to haue our portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at leaſt in the things of this life preſent: of which Dauid in the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teenth Pſalm ſpeaking, maketh his praier, thus,<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Vppe Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>diſappoint him, caſt him down: deliuer my ſoule from the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with thy ſword: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men by thine hand O Lord, from men of the world, who haue their portion in this life, whoſe bellies thou filleſt with thine hidde treaſures: their children haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and leaue the reſt of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for their children.</hi> Where hee ſpeaketh, as he meaneth, of the wicked, namelie, that they haue their portion in this life, and no where elſe; and that they haue already, as much as they ſhal haue, in this life preſent: for in the life to come they haue no portion. Anſwerably vnto that that Chriſt alſo warned thoſe good almeſ-men, forſooth, in the <hi>6.</hi> of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> which trumpetted the thing for the praiſe of men, <hi>Therefore,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>when thou giueſt thine almes, thou ſhalt not make a trumpet to be blown
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14652:10"/>before thee, as the hypocrites do in the Synagogues, &amp; in the ſtreets to be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of men. Verily I ſay vnto you, they haue their reward.</hi> That is, they haue already that they deſired, to witte, the praiſe of men; and this is all they ſhall haue: for beſides this verilie they ſhall haue nothing. And what then ſhal it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite the vngodly that they were wiſe, and rich, and honourable, and had peace, and proſperitie in this life, when this life is gone, and their portion ended, &amp; nothing remaineth for the life to come? the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of which eſtate anſwered his doubt, who in beholding the proſperitie of the wicked, had almoſt denied providence, till at the laſte, in acknowledgement of that which here is taught,<note place="margin">Claud.</note> he ſaith, <hi>Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntur in altum, vt lapſu graviore ruant, <hi>They are lifted vppe aloft, to haue the greater fall.</hi>
               </hi> As Dauid, to expreſſe his greateſt miſery, ſaith, <hi>He taketh me vp, and caſteth me downe againe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 102.</note> Euen as that we lift vp to caſt downe, we daſh all in pieces. And the beggers wo is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Prince his want. But, as he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14652:10"/>ſaith,<note place="margin">Sen. Theb.</note> 
               <hi>In ſervitutem cadere de regno graue eſt. <hi>Of king to become a caitife, that cuts the heart.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, but the wicked and vngodlie of the world haue wealth and welfare: and while they haue it, will ſome ſay, they are wel and happy. But this their happines, what euer they haue, in ſpite of all the wicked we deny, for firſt it ſhould be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen how they haue any thing. Not by promiſe: for that pertaineth vnto godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, by teſtimony of our Text, which ſaith ſignificantlie, that godlines hath the promiſe, and not vngodlines. How them? without promiſe. O miſerable theues &amp; robbers, which haue an heape of goodes ſo ill gotten.<note place="margin">Pſal. 24. v. 1.</note> For <hi>the earth is the Lords,</hi> &amp; he hath promiſed the ſame vnto the godlie, and againe,<note place="margin">Math. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are the meeke, for they ſhall inherit the earth. And everie creature of God is good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; nothing to be refuſed, if it be recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with thankſgiving. For it is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>by the worde of God, and prayer.</hi> But who giveth thankes, and who ſo receaueth the good
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14652:11"/>creatures of God, as good and lawfull; and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ome are they ſanctified by the ordinance and will of God, but to thoſe, as before he ſaith, <hi>which beleeue, and know the truth,</hi> that is, the godlie. For all the vngodlie of the world are yet in their pollution, and are deprived of all the creatures of the earth; polluting to themſelues everie good creature of God, in the abuſe, liue in the verie vſe of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and polluting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſay not now, becauſe <hi>ſtricto iure,</hi> as they ſay, by <hi>direct law,</hi> they haue no right in them. So Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths vinyard was good:<note place="margin">1. King. 21. Levit. 25.23. &amp; Num. 36.9. &amp; ſeq. &amp; 1. King. 21.</note> and Ahab had it. But, becauſe he was not of the tribe, beſides the intruſion, the forgerie, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, and murther committed, hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed himſelfe in the vnlawfull vſe of it. And this is the caſe of all the vngodlye: who, becauſe they are not of his tribe, who hath the right of inheritance in all theſe thinges, beſides the manifold abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they put them vnto after, they euen defile themſelues in the having of them. And ſo, not this, and that, as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diviſion of the legal pollutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14652:11"/>taught vs that out right in all thinges through our attainder was ſo taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, that by touching; almoſt, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king wee defiled our ſelues in them: but even the breath of their bodies, their life it ſelfe, &amp; all things are defiled to them? becauſe, to ſpeake the ſame thing againe, as <hi>light is come into the world, &amp; men loue darkeneſſe, roote the light:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioan. 3 19.</note> ſo liberty is come into the world, and men loue bondage, more then it: and the grace of adoption, whereby we become ſonnes (<hi>and if ſonnes,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle from a ground of their law; for in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell law of the Romans all the ſonnes ſucceeded together; <hi>then heyres, and heyres annexed with Ieſus Chriſt;</hi>) is refuſed of the vngodlie and vnbeleevers: who if they haue no part in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>who is the heyre of al thinges,</hi> as the Apoſtle teacheth to the Hebrewes; how woulde they haue right in any thing, and not ſtill remaine as children, and heires of the firſt Adam, caſt out of Paradiſe with his children, the verie bleſſing of the earth this day being turned into a curſe vnto
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14652:12"/>them, euen becauſe they haue no part in the ſecond Adam. Wherefore, let all the vngodlie of the world here learne to looke weſt vnto their theeviſh handes, &amp; care how to haue <hi>their hartes purified by faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 15.9. 2. Tim. 3.12.</note> &amp; to liue godly in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> that ſo they may be heires of the promiſe; and that, in the rich vngodlie eſpeciallie it may be ſeene for a wounder to the world how the camel creapeth through the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles eye, and that which is impoſſible <hi>with men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.30.</note> 
               <hi>is yet poſſible with God,</hi> the propheſie of Davis in <hi>22.</hi> Pſalme bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fulfilled in them. <hi>All the fat of the earth,</hi> &amp; thoſe that are filled with earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie felicitie, ſhall eate, as being nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Church,<note place="margin">verſ. 28.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhal bow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</hi> As before hee ſaith, <hi>All the endes of the earth ſhall remember the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and bee turned vnto the Lorde, &amp; all the kindreds of the nations ſhall worſhip before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which lowly ſubmiſſion vnto Ieſus Chriſt, and to the ſepter of his worde in the kingdome of his Church, if once we might ſee in the greate vngodlye of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14652:12"/>world, Lord, how manye ſinnes alſo would ſo be cut of, which dailie are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the good thinges of God, through the manifold abuſe of them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne and wickednes. And if wee ſee it not, as to ſeldome in deede is ſeene, ſo many ſinnes remaine of this ſort alſo, that better for them it were if beggers they had beene borne, and ſo had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to their liues end, then to anſwere this account before the great Iudge; the riches alſo <hi>of whoſe bountifulnes and patience they haue</hi> abuſed, <hi>not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2 4.5.6.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulnes of God leadeth them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: but they after their hardnes, &amp; hart that cannot repent, heape vnto themſelues wrath againſt the daye of wrath, and declaration of the iuſt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, who ſhall reward everie man according to his workes:</hi> open, or ſecret; to himſelfe, or others. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then, and there alſo ſhall bee revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led touching their title of poſſeſſion, how it faileth with God, which holdeth with men: which is a ſecret to the world, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14652:13"/>to worldlie mans hartes, but knowen vnto Gods;<note place="margin">Rom. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall iudge,</hi> as Paul ſaieth, <hi>the ſecrets of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Ieſus Chriſt according to my goſpell.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the good natured man alſo, and of greater ingenuitie, cannot eſcape with all his colours of naturall honeſtie and vertue, amiable in it ſelfe, and before the world,<note place="margin">Mark. 10.21.</note> but deſpiſed of God, becauſe it wanteth godlines. According as our Saviour ſaith in the ſixteenth of Luke, namely,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.16.</note> that <hi>that, which is loftie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, is abhomination in the ſight of God.</hi> And to ſay the verie truth, why ſhould God eſteeme them, or any thing in them, who never eſteemed him, but them ſelues, in all their liues? for looke we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe men with godlie wiſedome, and whither ſhal we ſee al their deſires, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes counſailes, and endevours direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but vnto themſelues; and to their owne pleaſures, praiſe, and profit, or to the profit of men like vnto themſelues. againſt whome, and whoſe workes, the former ſentence of Chriſt is as good, as againſt the praiers and almes of painted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14652:13"/>hypocrites.<note place="margin">Mat. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>Verilie I ſay vnto you they haue their reward:</hi> to wit, in this world, and with men; and they are fowlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved if they looke for more. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to conclude this point, if the wicked and vngodly, being empty and having nothing, haue no promiſe or hope of any things or having all thinges of the world, haue with God no lawful tenure and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation of the ſame; and farther, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting themſelues in the greate abuſe of them haue a heavier iudgment in time to come, the beſt of the vngodly not here excepted: what matterreth it what they haue, and what they are here for a while in this world, ſith at the laſt they looſe all, &amp; themſelues by a fearefull deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and nothing in the ende is founde gaine, but godlineſſe, <hi>which is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto all thinges,</hi> and at all times, as <hi>having the promiſe of this life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and of that that is to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here we muſt ſtay a little, at the leaſt to examine this, how the promiſe holdeth with the godly for the things of of this life: for of the things of the life to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14652:14"/>come there is no queſtion: the Apoſtle himſelfe in the <hi>15.</hi> of the firſt to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians vſing theſe words,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 25.29.</note> 
               <hi>If in this life only we haue hope in Chriſt, wee are of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the moſt miſerable.</hi> Where albeit he gathereth a moſt ſound conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for his preſent purpoſe, the handling of which I now omit, yet thus much he ſaieth withall by way of compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the godly and the vngodly, that we in this life are more miſerable then they. And if we looke vpon the afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s themſelues in their own nature, &amp; nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, and ſee no more, I grant it too. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Saints themſelues are weak-ſighted herein, and tender vpon the ſenſe of preſent ſorrows, <hi>no chaſtiſing for the preſent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note> as ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>ſeeming ioyous, but grieuous;</hi> they ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in their haſt they know not what; as if they were miſerable,<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.23. &amp; pſal. 116.11.</note> and others bleſſed; and they will reaſon this matter with God aboute the trueth of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. So Ieremie, but with leaue, and verie modeſtlie, in the <hi>12, O Lord,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Ier. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>if I diſpute with thee, thou art righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14652:14"/>yet let me talke with thee of thy iudgements: Wherefore doth the way of the wicked proſper? why are al they in wealth that rebelliouſly tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſe?</hi> and Abacuk in the firſt Chapter,<note place="margin">Abac. ca. 1.</note> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto God, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not tel how to ſet theſe togither, namely, the purity of Gods na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the proſperity of tranſgreſſours, and the miſery of the righteous. <hi>Thou art,</hi> ſaith he; <hi>of pure eies, and canſt not ſee euill: thou canſt not beholde wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes. Wherefore doſt thou looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tranſgreſſours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and holdeſt thy tongue when the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous then he?</hi> and Iob, and Dauid, two excellente perſonages, but much afflicted, were more impatient; and Iob, euen terrified, in the <hi>21: Euen when I remember,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I am afraide, and feare taketh holde on my fleſh. Wherefore do the wicked liue, and waxe old, &amp; grow in wealth?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 21.6, &amp; ſeq.</note> 
               <hi>their ſeede is eſtabliſhed in their ſight with them, and their generation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eies: Their houſes are peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able without feare and the rod of God
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14652:15"/>is not vpon them.</hi> And ſo foorth with a long and tedious narration vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of the great proſperity of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And David pathetically and abrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, as newly delivered out of this temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, beginneth his Pſalme thus, <hi>Yet God is good to Iſraell, even vnto ſuch as are of a cleane hart. Verily as for me my feete were almoſt gone;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> 
               <hi>my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings had well nigh ſlipt: and why? I was grieved at the wicked; I did ſee all the vngodly in ſuch proſperitie. For there are not knots vnto their death: but they are luſty and ſtrong. They are not in toile as other folke, neither are they plagued like other men.</hi> And then ſetting out more at large both their impiety and proſperity, as thinges not ſo agreeable in his iudgement, at the laſt he vſeth this <hi>Acclamation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Lo, theſe are the vngodly, theſe proſper in the world, &amp; theſe haue riches in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion.</hi> And then he ſheweth how weake he was, and how ill at the firſt hee tooke this matter.<note place="margin">verſ. 13.</note> 
               <hi>And I ſaide,</hi> ſaith this good man, <hi>then haue I cleanſed my heart in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14652:15"/>vaine, and waſhed my hands in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie. All the day long haue I beene puniſhed, and chaſtened every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> And ſo cleare is this thing, the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which haue the promiſe, ſometime, &amp; for the moſt part in ſuch aduerſitie; and the vngodly, which haue no promiſe, in ſuch proſperitie, that heereby they euen inſult ouer God, and his children, as in the <hi>15.</hi> verſe, <hi>Ecce generationem filiorum tuorum: <hi>Behold the generation of thy children:</hi>
               </hi> as if they ſhould ſay, who neede care much to be of the number, and their caſe no better. And yet ſtil, my brethren, we holde faſt this trueth, which heere is taught vs, namely, that godlineſſe hath the promiſe, not only of the life that is to come, but of this life preſent alſo. And the performance is good.</p>
            <p>But everie promiſe is kept, as it is made. And though this promiſe here is meant vnto the godlie, yet the ſame in preciſe tearmes is made vnto godlineſſe, as at the firſt was noted. That ſo the godlie might bee taught to aſſure them ſelues of the truth hereof, onely with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14652:16"/>
               <hi>Quatenus,</hi> and clauſe of reſtraint, and no otherwiſe, to wit, thus, ſo far as the are godlie; becauſe the godlie do want of their godlines. And as Paul ſaith of knowledge, which is a part of godlines, <hi>our knowledge is in part:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> ſo much more is it true of the whole, that our godlines is in part: &amp; it were a dangerous dreame to thinke otherwiſe. Wherefore wee accuſe not the purietie and ſincerity, but the perfection of godlines: and the moſt godlie wee ſay againe doe want of then godlines. So far therefore as wee are godlie, and doe keepe with God, ſo far he keepeth with vs, but when we breake with him, as too often we do, this alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the caſe with vs, but yet not with God. For then he taketh the rod in hand, which otherwiſe ſhould lie long enough, but for very neede: and, ſo that godlines might go with all, <hi>his delighte is in the proſperitie of his ſervants. Oh,</hi> ſaith he, in the <hi>48.</hi> of Eſaie, <hi>Oh that thou hadeſt harkened to my commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 48.18.</note> 
               <hi>then had thy proſperity bene as the floud, and thy righteouſnes as
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14652:16"/>the waues of the ſea.</hi> That is, they ſhould haue followed one vpon the other, as one waue of the ſea followeth an other, and gone alonge together as companions vnſeperable. And in the fourſkore and firſt Pſalme, <hi>Oh that my people had harkened vnto mee, and Iſraell had walked in my waies: I woulde ſoone haue humbled their enemies, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my hand againſt their adverſaries: the haters of the Lorde ſhoulde haue beene ſubiect vnto him: but their time</hi> (to wit, time of the proſperitye of his people) <hi>this their time ſhould haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured for ever. And God would haue fed them with the fatte of wheate; and with honey out of the rocke woulde I haue ſatiſfied thee.</hi> But if wee harken not vnto God, &amp; walke not in his waies, what then <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then thus, and it is inchided in the condition of the promiſe vnto Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, and all the faithfull, in the fourſkore and ninth Pſalme, thus, <hi>But if his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren forſake my law, and walke not in my iudgementes; if they breake my ſtatutes, and keepe not my comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14652:17"/>dementes. I will viſite their offences with the rodde, and their ſinne vvith ſcourges. Nevertheleſſe my lovinge kindnes will I not vtterly take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him: not ſuffer my truth to faile.</hi> So that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hee, which alſo puniſheth our vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, is true in his promiſe, and his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſe remaineth ſtill, with it, ſhall I ſay? yea, in it. Heere is a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: and yet no myſterie vnto the godlye; which feele and finde their vngodlineſſe ſo to bee chaſtened by the hande of God, with ſuch a fatherlie good will and care of them, that hee turneth them hereby from their vngodlines, to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d faſt in the covenant; and al that furthereth this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is therefore bleſſed. Bleſſed is the ſickeneſſe, bleſſed are the ſores, bleſſed are <hi>the woundes</hi> of ſuch <hi>a friend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 27.6.</note> 
               <hi>yea, better then the kiſſes of an enemie.</hi> This I take it is the meaninge of that league and Covenaunt in the ſecond of Hoſea, <hi>And in that day,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>will I make a Covenant for them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>with the wilde beaſtes, and with the fowles of the heauen, and with that that cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14652:17"/>vpon the earth: and I will breake the bow, and the ſwoord, and the battail out of the earth, and will make them to ſleepe ſafely.</hi> Not that there ſhall not bee annoyances to theſe confederates in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; in earth, aboue, &amp; below, &amp; rounde about them; nor that the ſword ſhall not be whet, &amp; bow bent, &amp; the battail ſet againſt them in all the earth; for who in the earth more afflicced then wee? but, that the intent of the enemy ſhall be defeated, &amp; theſe inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of miſchiefe, prepared for their hurt, ſhal be found in the end to do them good. <hi>O Aſhur, the rod of my wrath,</hi> ſaith the Lord by the Prophet, <hi>and the ſtaffe in their handes is mine indignation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 10.5.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſende him to a diſſembling nation, and I will giue him a charge, againſt the people of my wrath, to take the ſpoile, and to take the pray, &amp; to tread them vnder feete, as the mire in the ſtreete. But he thinketh not ſo: but hee imagineth to deſtroy and to cut of not a few nations.</hi> The purpoſe of the Lord, &amp; his worke was, by the rod of the Aſſirians in iuſtice, &amp; iudgement, to puniſh the ſinnes of Ieruſalem &amp; Iuda for their amendment: as Ieremie ſaith, <hi>Let thine owne wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14652:18"/>correct thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>and thy turninges back reprooue thee; know therefore, &amp; behold that it is an evill thing and bitter that thou haſt forſaken the Lord thy God and that my feare is not in thee, ſaith the Lord God of hoſtes.</hi> But the bent of the Aſſirian was barely to deſtroy, and to ſet vp his great name by mighty deſtructions. Thus the enimies ſhall whet their ſwoord, and bend their bow, &amp; make readie the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail for our deſtruction; they ſhall kill, and leade captiue, &amp; devide the ſpoiles; &amp; yet no harme doone: for the Prophecie of Eſaias ſhall be fulfilled,<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall not hurt, nor deſtroy in al the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine of my holines.</hi> The reaſon, <hi>For the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters that couer the ſea.</hi> This plentifull know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge doth keepe all ſafe. Which Paul alſo aſcribeth to our loue of God; who cannot but loue him, after that we haue knowen him, and his loue towardes vs; according as hee hath choſen vs before, and called vs with an holy calling,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tim. 1.9.</note> to know, loue, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him in all true holines. Wherefore in the <hi>8.</hi> to the Romans moſt comfortablie &amp; moſt plainely to this purpoſe he ſaieth, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14652:18"/>we know that all thinges worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the beſt vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> 
               <hi>euen to them that are called of purpoſe.</hi> Where doubtleſſe the Apoſtle meaneth not ſo chiefelie of the thinges which properlie are good, as of thoſe, which might be hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if the purpoſe of men, and the nature of the things ſhould be reſpected. But ſuch is the worke of godlines, or rather of God for the godly, whome he hath loued, &amp; called ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to purpoſe; &amp; they know him, &amp; loue him, &amp; ſerue him in holines; that for their ſakes <hi>according to the warking,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Philip. 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>whereby he is able to ſubdue all things vnto himſelfe; &amp; to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the light to ſhine out of darkenes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.6.</note> he alſo ſubdueth vnto himſelfe, &amp; his, the nature of theſe evill thinges, and turneth them vnto their good, ſo bringing light out of darknes, ioy out of griefe, grace out of ſin, delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of deſtruction, &amp; life out of death it ſelfe: that the true cauſe of our rejoycing may ſo appeare, as Paul in the third of the firſt to the Corinthians ſheweth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.21.22.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore</hi> ſaith he; <hi>let no man reioyce in men: for all thinges are yours: whether it be Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world: or life
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14652:19"/>or death; whether they be things preſent, or things to come, all are yours, &amp; yee are Chriſtes, &amp; Chriſt is Gods.</hi> Wherefore, my deare brethren, let vs be Chriſts, as Chriſt is Gods; that is, Chriſtians in deede, as in name we are, &amp; all things are ours, to ſerue vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.13.</note> &amp; to miniſter vnto our good, &amp; nothing ſhall hurt vs: <hi>we ſhall walke,</hi> as he ſaieth, <hi>vpon the lion &amp; aſpe, the young lion &amp; the dragon ſhall he treade vnder feete;</hi> &amp; this miracle in a ſort ſhal ſtil be ſeene &amp; felt of vs, of which out ſaviour ſaith, <hi>They ſhall take away ſerpents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 16.19.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; if they ſhall drinke of any deadly thing, if ſhall not hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And ſuch reioicing hath godlines. And why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould we fear a flout, to be called godly of the vngodly, beggers brats, &amp; no better, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> haue nothing, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſe of nothing: neither in this life, nor in the life to come.</p>
            <p>And yet leaſt heere they may ſtande at a bay with vs, and ſay againe that wee haue nothing; as many of vs, yea moſt of vs, haue leſſe in the things of this life; yet this is not true, that we haue nothing, and fewe of the godly, not Lazarus himſelfe, but hath ſome thing, according to the trueth of this which the Apoſtle teatheth vs, that <hi>Godlines</hi> hath
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14652:19"/>the promiſe of this life alſo. For if he haue nothing elſe, yet he hath life it ſelfe, and the ſame more perfectly, then any of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the worlde. For euery thing may be ſaid to be had, according to the vſe, &amp; perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vſe. For if I holde a treaſure in my hande, which is faſt ſealed to mee in a bagge, I may rather be ſaide to handle it, then to haue it. Or, if I be in an houſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any comfortable vſe of that houſe, in which I am; it may better bee ſaide to haue me, then I it. And ſo likewiſe according to the perfection and excellencie of each vſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing may be ſaide to be more, or leſſe perfectly had of vs. So Lazarus, with his trumbes and rags, becauſe he had a godlie life, and a comfortable life with God, and a ſweet expectation of the life to come, he was more aliue, then the rich, with his robes, depriued of all true comforte in all his life. And I know not how; yes, it is the bleſſing of God, which can multiplie in vſe a little, and ſo make it much, much better, and ſo and in this ſenſe, much bigger, then the far and large portion of the wicked. And in this ſenſe I doubt not but Dauid ſaith in the <hi>37</hi> Pſalme, <hi>Better is a little,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.16.</note> 
               <hi>which each righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:14652:20"/>deeds, which they haue vngodly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and of al their cruel ſpeakings, which wicked ſinners haue ſpoken againſt him.</hi> I adde, and his: for he, and his muſt go togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And therefore let vs alſo, my brethren, as ioine-workers with God, for the glory of God, &amp; honour of godlines, ſpeake againſt them, and do againſt them, euery man, as he can do moſt: that al the vngodly of the earth <hi>like droſſe</hi> may be conſumed,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. verſ. 119.</note> the godlie in Ieſus Chriſt increaſed and comforted, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion maintained, and God aboue al glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. To whom be glory, dominion, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie both now, and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="Greek_text_bound_with_sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:14652:20"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14652:21"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14652:21"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14652:22"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14652:22"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14652:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14652:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14652:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14652:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
